Guide to the Jarvis House records, 1946-1981 (bulk 1966-1977)
Duke University. University Archives
Jarvis House records 1946-1981 (bulk 1966-1977)
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. Jarvis House.
1 linear feet Extent: 1000 Items
Jarvis House, named for former North Carolina Governor Thomas J. Jarvis, was built of white pressed brick and Indiana sandstone and roofed with green tile. It was completed and occupied in October 1912. The collection contains the records of Jarvis House, a residence hall for undergraduate female students at Duke University.
RL.01647
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Jarvis House records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1980.
Historical Note
The Jarvis Residence Hall, named for former North Carolina Governor Thomas J. Jarvis, was considered to be cutting-edge in architectural design, adding great aesthetical value to Trinity College's campus (now the East Campus of Duke University). Like its nearby twin, Aycock Hall, Jarvis was built of white pressed brick and Indiana sandstone and roofed with green tile. When completed and occupied in October 1912, the building was three stories high and divided into five separate sections by solid firewalls extending from the ground to the roof. Jarvis had such amenities as a large social room, two complete kitchens, and a pressing room on each floor. Built to house 120 students, it was home to men from 1912 to 1930. Jarvis Hall also housed the campus post office between 1912 and 1928. In 1930, the new West Campus opened and what had been the Trinity College campus (now East Campus) became the Woman's College of Duke University.
Jarvis House has been a non-selective women's residence hall since around 1930. In 1977, during an effort to equalize the balance of men and women on west campus, Housing Affairs administrators proposed to move residents of Jarvis Hall to housing blocks on West Campus. Jarvis residents protested the move and remained on East campus next to the Carr Building and West Duke Building.
As a residential unit, Jarvis House was at times governed by the Office of Student Affairs, Office of Housing Management, the Women's Student Government Association, the Residential Life Committee, the Community Council of the Woman's College, and the Association of Independent Houses.
Collection Overview
Contains the records of Jarvis House, a residence hall for undergraduate female students at Duke University. Types of materials include correspondence, programming notes, reports, fliers, minutes, newsletters, photographs, rosters, song lyrics, scrapbooks, and financial records. Major subjects include Trinity College history, Duke University history, women college students, student life, and general governance of residence halls. Materials range in date from 1946-1981, (bulk 1966-1977). The three scrapbooks were created by Jarvis House residents. Because the original scrapbooks were in poor condition, items were removed and placed in archival folders for preservation. The scrapbook dated 1960-1961 is intact.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
College students -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University; Duke University -- History; Duke University -- Students; Duke University -- Students -- Social conditions; Duke University. Woman's College -- History; Dormitories -- North Carolina -- Durham; Residence and education; Scrapbooks; Student housing -- North Carolina -- Durham; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--History; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--Students; Women college students -- North Carolina -- Durham
Related Material
Arts and Sciences Council records
Duke University Archives
Alspaugh House records
Duke University Archives
Association of Independent Houses records
Duke University Archives
Baldwin Federation records
Duke University Archives
Bassett House records
Duke University Archives
Brown House records
Duke University Archives
Bunch of Guys records
Duke University Archives
Few Federation records
Duke University Archives
Gilbert-Addoms Residence Hall records
Duke University Archives
Giles House records
Duke University Archives
Mirecourt House records
Duke University Archives
Pegram House records
Duke University Archives
S.H.A.R.E. records
Duke University Archives
Warwick House records
Duke University Archives
York House records
Duke University Archives
Bibliography
Willimon. William H. We Work Hard, We Play Hard: A Report for the President, and the Provost, and the Vice President for Student Life of Duke University,
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Correspondence, 1970-1977
  - Curriculum and courses, 1969-1970
  - Damage reports, 1975-1978
  - Federation establishment, circa 1976
  - Flyers, 1981
  - Governing bodies, memos, notes, rules, 1968-1977
  - House meeting and house council notes, 1968-1969
  - House meeting and house council notes, 1967-1968, 1969-1977
  - Newsletters, 1965-1979
  - Open House reports, 1968
  - Photographs, 1956, 1974-1978
  - President's report, 1946-1947
  - Programming, undated
  - Relocation, 1977
  - Rosters and personnel assignments, 1967-1977
  - Songs, undated
  - Scrapbook, circa 1953-1956, pages 1-30 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1953-1956, pages 31-50
  - Scrapbook, 1960-1961
  - Scrapbook, 1964-1965
  - Financial records, 1966-1970